A Guide to the Ross Family Correspondence, 1861-1864
Library of Virginia
- Correspondence, January-February 1863 (Folder 8)
  - Letter, 18 February 1863, from James Ross to Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, sending news of camp life., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 24 February 1863, from Daniel Ross to his sister, Fluvanna County, providing camp and personal news., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 25 February 1863, from James Ross to Nela F. Ross, Fluvanna County, sending camp and personal news. He notes that the regiment is moving south., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 27 February 1863, from Luther C. White, near Guinea Station, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, sending camp news and stating that rumor is the Union army will cross the Rappahannock River when the weather gets warm., 3 pages.
- Correspondence, March-May 1863 (Folder 9)
  - Letter, 5 March 1863, from James Ross, near Petersburg, Virginia, to Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, sending camp news and informing her how friends and family in the regiment are faring., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 15 March 1863, from James Ross, near Petersburg, to Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, sending camp and personal news., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 20 March 1863, from James Ross, near Petersburg, to his sister, Fluvanna County, sending regimental and army news, including movements of various brigades., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 30 March 1863, from James Ross, Southampton County, Virginia, to Mary Eliza Ross, Fluvanna County, informing her of the regiment's move towards Suffolk and speculations. He notes that the Union army in Mississippi is focusing on Vicksburg. He hopes for peace by summer., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 7 April 1863, from James Ross, Southampton County, to Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing Nathaniel's death at home, deaths in camp, and news about the regiment's movements towards Suffolk., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 24 April 1863, from James Ross, Nansemond County, Virginia, to Mary Eliza Ross, Fluvanna County, describing the fighting around Suffolk, providing camp news, and hoping that someone might be able to come to camp and take his winter clothes home., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 10 May 1863, from James and Daniel Ross, near Richmond, to Nela F. Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing the regiment's departure from Suffolk, General Lee's victory at the battle of Chancellorsville, and news of a Union cavalry into Fluvanna County., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 11 May 1863, from James Ross, near Richmond, to Mary Eliza Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing someone to get their winter clothes, Union troops in Fluvanna County, Stonewall Jackson's death, views on the war, and camp news., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 17 May 1863, from James Ross, Hanover County, Virginia, to Nela F. Ross, Fluvanna County, complaining that he has not received any mail from home, discussing the regiment's movements, and other camp news., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 19 May 1863, from Richard P. White, Hanover County, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, discussing the Union cavalry raid on Fluvanna County, and camp news., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 27 May 1863, from Daniel Ross, Hanover County, to Lucy W. Ross, Fluvanna County, commenting on camp life, news about Vicksburg, Mississippi, his hopes for peace, and the African American attitude towards the Union troops raiding Fluvanna County., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 29 May 1863, from James Ross, Hanover County, to Lucy W. Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing camp news, news of fighting around Vicksburg, a brigade review by General George Pickett, and the regiment's new hats., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 30 May 1863, from Richard P. White, Hanover County, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, discussing camp news, the marriage of a love interest of White's, news of Vicksburg, and speculation of fighting the enemy., 4 pages.
- Correspondence, June, August, November-December 1863 (Folder 10)
  - Letter, 1 June 1863, from James Ross, Hanover County, to Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning Vicksburg, the contrast in the military situation from the year before, a religious revival in camp, and efforts to get back pay for his deceased brother Nathaniel., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 7 June 1863, from James Ross to Mary Eliza Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing the activities of his regiment, news of Union raids in King and Queen and King William Counties, Virginia, and news that General Lee is moving north., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 11 June 1863, from Daniel Ross, near Culpeper Court House, to his sister, Fluvanna County, commenting on the army's movement northward and his speculation on its aim. he also includes camp news., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 15 June 1863, from James Ross, near Culpeper Court House, to Nela F. Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning news about the regiment's movements and camp news., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 20 June 1863, from Daniel Ross, near Warrenton[?], Virginia, to his sister, Fluvanna County, informing her of the regiment's movements and sending camp news., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 21 June 1863, from James[?] Ross, Ashby's Gap, Virginia, to Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning movement of the Confederate and Union armies, including news of a fight at Winchester, Virginia., 2 pages, incomplete.
  - Letter, 30 June 1863, from Daniel Ross, near Chambersburg, Pennsylvania, to his sister, Fluvanna County, concerning the army's invasion of Pennsylvania, including the local inhabitants' fright and news that General Richard Ewell has invested Harrisburg, Pennsylvania., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 2 August 1863, from Richard P. White to his cousin, Fluvanna County, containing news of the regiment, including the possible return of prisoners from the battle of Gettysburg., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 10 August 1863, from Richard P. White to his cousin, Fluvanna County, sending camp news and personal news., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 1 November 1863, from James B. T. Bragg, Richmond, sending personal news and offering a look at Richmond during the Civil War., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 14 December 1863, from Richard P. White, Richmond, to his brother, Fluvanna County, discussing the regiment's movements between Petersburg and Richmond and mentioning General Pickett., 2 pages.
- Correspondence, 1864 (Folder 11)
  - Letter, 19 February 1864, from Richard P. White[?], Richmond, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, containing camp news., 4 pages, incomplete.
  - Letter, 21 March 1864, from James B. T. Bragg, Richmond, to is cousin, Fluvanna County, commenting on his life in Richmond and describing his work on the railroad, as well as personal news., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 23 April 1864, from Richard P. White, Richmond, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, commenting on regimental news and news on the military situation in Virginia, including another possible invasion of Maryland., 4 pages.
- Correspondence, 1936 (Folder 12)
  - Letter, 22 January 1936, from Dr. J. Ross Perkins, Richmond, providing genealogical information on James Eastin Ross, Nathaniel Wheeler Ross, and William Daniel Ross, and the Ross family in connection with the Civil War era letters., 1 leaf.